Yeah, it's.
Perfect. Ready.
Right.
So welcome.
Let's continue where we stopped yesterday.
So.
First of all, uh.
Little assignment for everybody.
So the assignment is to post it in the
class because in the class there is the
option to have assignments.
We will not formally review so feel free,
but please may do it.
Was a it is a part of the journey. Uh.
Pick up at least two programming
languages.
I can give you a number,
at least I will mention a few now and
investigate possibly with the AI help by
posing the right questions,
whether the programming language.
Supports lexical closures and if the
support is complete or there is some
approximation, spoiler Pascal so.
Don't use Pascal because I'm about
spoiled.
Uh allows to uh a function to return a
procedure or a function.
A procedure in Pascal is a a function
returning void, so and Pascal.
In fact, did allow to return the function,
but in a way in which basically you can
refer only to the environment in the
module. OK, so basically the scope,
the lifetime of the scope.
Of the of the function that you return is
the same as the container.
So there is no technical issue in in
having essentially a closure because the
rule by which you can return a function
being restricted to avoid complication in
the implementation.
OK,
so technically it implements a little bit
lexical closures, but not entirely. OK,
so this is an example of partial
implementation.
So you can investigate C, JavaScript,
JavaScript. We basically introduce.
We know it's available.
You can pick up MLF sharp, Visual Basic,
C#, Java.
Rust, Python, Lua.
Pearl.
I mean pick up even programming languages
that are not so popular these days.
I mean Fortune, Cobol.
PowerShell.
Um.
Bash C shell because that reality also
shell are in fact scripting languages,
but they are Turing equivalent.
So in principle you can have also their
lexical closure, so investigate.
And and and then maybe at some point we
will ask for your outputs so that we can.
I will post the form in in the assignment
so that you can.
Upload the if you want the finding.
It's not mandatory,
but we encourage you so that we can have
some discussion and we can keep going
with this experimentation, OK?
Now we found out that the scoping names
are important.
Scope is a an essential element of
programming because scope defines the.
Scope where a name has some meaning and
the meaning means it has a value,
it has a type and and and implicitly even
though with static scope the scope is
defined.
Independently from the execution.
Nevertheless,
we all know that the scope will affect
also the execution.
We should briefly introduce the the the
notion of activation records.
That we commented that activation records
are a key structure that it is commonly
used in.
Basically all modern languages to
implement the automatic allocation and
allocation of the memory which is induced
by the scope.
Today we start talking about the memory
management in a deeper way.
Which means that we start with the
explicit memory allocation,
so malloc and free of C,
new and delete of C, C++ and so on. OK,
so where the programmer is responsible
for allocating.
And they're locating the memory.
And and then we introduce 2 automatic
techniques for managing the memory.
The first one is reference counting.
Reference counting is a very simple idea.
And then we move on to a little bit more
sophisticated approach,
which is the garbage collection, OK.
Um, of course I will refer.
So already during the last class we
discussed that the memory is a stream of
cells. OK,
then it's up to the language reinterpret
those bytes as data structures.
And in fact the layout of the memory is
crucial for instance for interoperability.
So at some point we will start talking
about marshalling and marshalling that
are common serialisation and
deserialisation which is similar are
common.
A way of allow different programming
language to share data structures and if
you share CPU values,
so integer for instance or double that
easy because it's the CPU which ensure
interoperability.
But even if you take a very simple data
structure such as.
You know coordinate XY,
then you can store Y&
X or XY and the compiler will decide this.
And so if you have two different
compilers and you want to share the
memory,
then the reinterpretation of the bytes
depends upon the compiler and there are.
And that.
There are standards in the calling
conventions and also there we will see
that there are interesting aspects.
So the memory that we are talking today
is the sequence of byte memory.
At some point we will restart talking
about the memory in terms of how do we
lay out objects,
classes and and and types.
But first we need to introduce all the.
Typing operations that allow us to define
types in our languages. OK, so.
Let's start the uh.
I want to simulate a malloc re execution
in C AR style.
Can you generate an empty heap?
Visually.
And then I will ask for allocate and the
allocate and you display the updated heap.
This is really an experiment.
I don't know if if. I think it will work,
but uh.
We'll see. OK,
so I'm pretty sure that all of you know
that malloc and free are the basic C
operations to allocate this.
Pleasely dynamic memory and the allocate.
We already commented that static memory
can be.
Computed at compile time and it will be
allocated statically,
so for all the execution and we just
commented that automatic memory
parameters,
local variables can be allocated and they
allocated on the stack. OK,
so basically today we start talking about
the heap.
Which is the portion,
typically the largest portion of.
Memory management of a of a processor is
where dynamic memory gets allocated.
Notice that because the memory is a very
long stream,
there is the problem that if you make the
stack grow.
Eventually you may bump into the heap,
so the compiler has to decide the the
maximum size of the stack,
because otherwise it will be impossible
to allocate the heap or vice versa.
OK and.
This is the main and basic reason why you
may get Stack Overflow errors.
So if you in your program you use
recursion and the recursion generates too
many activation records on the stack.
You may keep the the maximum size for the
stack and and you will get some error the
stack overflow error.
So far so good. I will say OK.
So we got 1000 slots in in our heap.
And and I'm I'm about to to discuss the
very first implementation,
which is actually part of the C
programming language book,
which is the original Kenny and Ricci
programming book.
And I encourage you to go and find the
implementation and read implementation
because malloc and free are easy to
implement and it is very very instructive
to learn how to manage the heap because
you may be.
Convinced that the heap allocation is
some magic or that the malloc is
basically no cost operation in term of
execution and when you start posing
yourself.
How can I implement the malloc given an
array of bytes?
You will quickly ends up understanding
that you will need some data structure to
manage the memory because at some point
you need to understand which blocks.
Are allocated and which blocks are still
free.
Now we all know that programs tend to
allocate and deallocate memory rather
frequently.
There are programming languages such as.
Java or.
net C in particular inherits so many
things from Java which basically made the
same choices that actually allocates
tremendously amount and they allocate
amount of data, for instance in Java.
You all sum up strings,
you concatenate string,
and you may remember that strings are
read only, so they're not buffers.
And when you sum 2 strings,
a new strings will get allocated and
therefore.
The original 2 strings,
if they are not anymore needed,
they can be freed. OK,
so the heap is a continuous place where
you get allocation, the location,
allocation, the location,
allocation and the location. OK,
so this has some implication in terms of
the policies and the cost of management.
In the data structure,
so let me uh my move Malloc.
My look then.
OK, let's see the output of a Malloc 10.
Uh, so why this thing compute?
How will you manage a single product by a
new Mallon 10 months?
Anyone.
To the expansion that it updates the the
and we.
So for example at the start,
I see that they want to target 10 bytes,
10 bytes hopefully is smaller than the.
Oh, let's say even 10 kilobytes. Honestly,
I mean that I said 10 just because I say.
I saw 1000 so.
And whatever he said.
Like.
Um, please.
So you yes. So you said OK,
we need a structure.
Where where do we store this data
structure?
And then the stack gets allocated and
allocated.
So how can we pretend that this will last?
So we need to build.
Based on the structure that you I'm
getting from the output here and where do
we store?
So you know what the heap initially is.
And right.
So because we have heap is empty,
am I wasting memory if I use those bytes?
No.
OK, because we see that it's empty,
it's there where it's allocated.
So I can be a data structure using the
heap itself.
This particular data structure has a name
and the name is.
Free list.
Which also hints you in the fact that
probably the quickest way to make another
structure which is made by Vox is to use
a single linked list.
Right, because uh,
maybe starts always at the same place.
So if I have the the freeze pointer at
the beginning,
I can still browser the list of the free
blocks and since those are free blocks.
I can write in in in that memory the next
pointer to the next block and so on. OK,
so now the three the blocks are size 32
bytes or now this.
It's perhaps even too detailed because
it's simulated also the alignment because
in the memory you you can't really
allocate a single byte because this view
requires you to align to some.
Multiple of two value.
The other side is 16 bytes,
so at least the other of the free list
and actually allocated bytes are.
Indicated in the map. So now we got to OK.
Let's say, um.
Uh.
Void star.
B2 equal.
Malloca.
32.
And void star.
B3 equal malloc 64.
So now I'm allocating few other bytes.
See.
So now I've asked to allocate blocks and
the out is very easy because you go to
the top of the list,
which is at the beginning of the the heap,
you have the first.
Block which is let's go back.
The first block was here that this was
the heap when we started.
The first two blocks are have been
allocated so the the free list pointer
will.
Point to the first three block and the
size is so this one.
Is 976 bytes. OK,
so basically the list includes the
pointer,
the next and the size of the three block.
And we said this is not costing anything
to us because we're using the free space
available in memory.
But it's not entirely a free ride because
by now, remembering algorithms,
you should already have guessed that
there is some cost and the cost is linear
of model. So if you leave the.
Thinking that allocation is super fast,
easy, that is untrue because.
You have to all the trees, but wow.
But now we still don't have a problem.
We allocated continuously.
So again I have the first.
Model of 10. This is the model of 32.
This is the model of 64.
We know the addresses in the memory,
etcetera, and then we have a single block,
so speed constant.
We will see that this strategy of
offending it is very good in a form of
garbage collection.
Let me so now I want to try a free.
P2 as proposed by by the way. OK,
so now I'm reading the point of block 2.
Now things are getting more interesting
because I decided to use block 2 because
it's in between the block one and block 3.
So now.
The situation is the one that is depicted
depicted here. You see allocated, empty,
allocated.
We got a hole in in our tape and.
Because this is the free.
And we also our free list points now to
block one and then.
Inside there will be a pointer to block 3,
which is the the largest block.
So if we iterate this process of allocate,
the allocate, allocate, the allocate,
the list may become very complicated and
the heat will.
Rodman.
So the risk is that if you sum up all the
bytes that are still market free,
you have a lot of memory,
but then your program tries to malloc a
block large large enough which.
Technically it's impossible and you will
get an end.
OK, so.
First thing that we learn by looking at
this and this is coming from the 70s and
we're still using it,
the free list approach.
The what what happens is that you may
have internal fragmentation of the data
structure,
which I think is something that you
already studied in a different course
memory fragmentation.
Architectures. Yeah, you're right.
And what is the solution in when you have
fragmentation in architectures?
Defragment that. OK,
so can we defragment our knee?
Do you think it is regional?
Hmm.
You can. I mean, don't worry,
you can in case I will translate.
So is it fast? Yes, that's the point.
So in architectures,
the number of cycles for doing anything
inside an operating systems system.
Are significant,
so you can pay the cost of moving blocks
of bytes from one part of the memory to
the other part of the memory.
But in this case it will be too much
expensive because.
We are at the instruction level of the
CPU,
so if we have a reorganization of the
heap to compact and restore things.
The risk is that you will end up needing
so much cycles then that will be
basically unacceptable in terms of the
performance. OK,
so but this has consequences,
so for instance.
In C for instance,
there are programming patterns that
encourage you to allocate multiple each.
So basically instead of saying I have a
very large big heap, one big heap,
you start changing and say you know what,
I start allocating the memory in charts,
big chart that's one MB and I have the
first heap of one MB and when I exhaust
these heap of one MB,
I allocate another heap.
For one MB and when the one MB,
the first one megabyte heap is empty,
I throw away everything and I will start
to reduce the impact of adding for each
allocation to jump across.
Thousands,
because if I do man lock free man lock
free thousand times,
you may end up with a very long long list.
Yes,
of course there are some optimization if
I find out that two blocks that are.
Three and an addition,
then I can join them in a single block.
OK, that I can try.
It will cost a little bit,
but still it's accepted.
So can you see another reason?
Because moving these blocks by the.
To fill the gap is not a good idea.
Perfect.
If I start moving and the program
directly has pointers or references.
So basically pointers in C you can print
the address.
In in Java are there,
but basically you don't see them,
but nevertheless it's still a memory
address even though you can't do much the
data. So if I move around the memory,
I end up with a big problem.
I have to find all the pointers to the
block.
And rewrite the pointer so that they will
point to the new location.
So compacting is not just a matter of an
algorithm to reorganize the bytes into
other structure.
I also have to ensure that all the
pointers will stay safe otherwise.
You will break the whole system and
that's a problem. OK, so basically,
as you can see,
even in the simplest form of memory
management, the free list,
we already bump into a number of problems
that you have to take into account.
Both when you are programming,
I don't know video game programming or
when you read the program generated
because memory is the most used thing in
a program.
Everything in the program goes by
allocating, allocating, allocating,
navigating, browsing,
the reference appointed, copy,
a value from here to there,
copy back from there to here and so on.
OK, so basically.
This is the most used data structure of
your program, the heap,
and so you have to pay attention that
bogus situation may not keep too much the
performance of your system.
And that's a big, big problem.
So you have always to pay attention.
You want a real world example,
you know the two main game consoles.
Two of the three main consoles for video
gaming are PlayStation and Xbox.
Xbox was launched in 2001 by Microsoft
and you get what they just launched.net.
So at some point they said OK,
you have to write computer games using.
net.
OK.
And and and at some point Microsoft
released a different virtual machine than
the standard one.
So there was the common length runtime
for normal programs and then there was a
different runtime for.
The Xbox and what was the difference?
The memory management because the the
memory management in a game may generate
so at every frame of a computer game.
So this means hundreds time.
For a second may heat up to 30,
000 objects.
OK, so every single loop of a game,
the game internally represents all the
resources, the 3D, the the textures,
the the physics engine, etcetera.
Every so everything that is represented
typically in the graph, this graph.
There is a module in the program which
basically read the graphs and generate
the frame to be sent to the graphics so
that you can see your beautiful game and
and at every single frame you will end up
touching 30,000.
Objects.
OK, in the average you can be unlocked.
All your gamers need to know because when
you see the game lag here,
that is typically because either you are
trying to load an asset from the disk or
you're touching for that particular frame
to make objects OK and.
When I was working to Xbox and to Kinect,
we were counting every single operation
to ensure that that you stay inside the
time slot by.
That and age of operation to ensure the
maximum performance of the game. OK,
so all this to say, OK,
memory management is essential is.
I mean if I look at the programs,
the programs basically read.
Files and and so parts and be free and
and then it's executing out and therefore
they use that structure.
Therefore the memory from time to time
they start writing down.
In the future, in a future class,
we will spend some time talking about the
persistent memory,
but let me because I think it's a good
moment to share this message right now.
I know that you've been told that the
disk is bad and that this case slow is
not entirely true anymore.
SSD drives and there are even faster
technologies than the SSDs now almost
match the performance of the memory.
So nowadays it is possible to write
programs.
That writes straight on the disk and the
performance is basically the same as they
were using the memory. OK,
if if you some of you are programmers,
look for a library which is called Ross
DB. You will find on them.
It was has been developed by.
Originated by Google,
then it has been maintained by Facebook
and it is basically a persistent hash
table.
OK and and there you you you do the hash
table operations and those are persisted
on this that library has been designed.
And uh, develop it. Um.
We sort state this in mind.
So all the algorithms are being designed
to be super fast and not taking over
mechanical drive, OK.
One last comment,
exactly these data structures.
I use it into all your drives.
Because you think that your driver by now
is your solid-state driver is a driver,
but it's not.
Actually that's an ungraded system.
Actually I contributed to do two of them
and it does.
Because they have very interesting and
fascinating algorithms because if you
keep powering your disk drive,
it will lose all the data once a week.
So there is a small thread inside your
drive which basically rewrite all the
sets.
And once a week,
and you know you've got a lot of
algorithms like this because inside
you've got even bytes and you have to
manage it and to ensure because you know
that if you write inside a NAND drive.
You are basically consuming a little bit
at the gate and you can't write for in
the same place because you were in source
to the cell.
Then this small very small operating
system inside the disk drive basically
turns and.
Copy blocks around so that the drive is
consuming heavily.
And so in this way you're you're you're
you're OK that your drive will not finish
working suddenly because you finished
with the maximum number of writing in
your disk. OK.
And in fact, if you look at your drive,
typically you have at least twice the
capacity of true space and the extra
capacity is used to stretch the lifetime
of your drive. OK,
all the algorithms inside your drives are
basically memory management arguments.
Algorithm that move blocks around with
very similar considerations.
And of course they must be more and more
efficient.
And so we'll spend some time later
talking about how do we access.
The disk because access to the disk has
changed in the last 10 years and I think
that servers even allow for persistent
memory run points.
So even the fact that RAM is volatile,
technically it is ending.
So since 2017 there is a standard that
allows you to insert memory modules in
server that are the system.
OK, so no saving.
You simply dump the memory of the
processor. No more files. That's it. OK,
right. So this is basically the the point.
So you have the free list and so the cost
is proportionately the length of the list
and.
If the heap is big enough,
you may end up having thousands of set
because you're always when when I ask.
So let let me do another example.
I hope I computed things rightly.
Uh.
Avoid star.
Before equal malloc 8.
And see if I'm right. So now I'm asking.
8 bytes and I and I have a space for 32
bytes that have been freed.
So.
I love this thing. OK,
so the block one is the malloc of eight
that is on B4 and.
There is the leftover from the split.
Which is a good example of the fact that
any all the times when you are located,
you typically are not lucky enough to
find a block which is the the same size
of the requested.
Allocation to be done and So what happens
is you split the the block.
And so, but now if I'm free, if I free.
Before.
Now I started with a free list of of two
elements. I've got still two elements.
Now I may have three elements even though
two are ads.
OK, so uh.
Oh,
actually she implemented the more
efficient.
So actually she mentioned back the blocks,
but that dependent depends on how smart
the memory algorithm management is. OK.
The the the canning and enrich
implementation.
So the original C model of free
implementation didn't do the separate
operation.
So basically you end up having multiple
blocks even though they were.
OK, OK,
so that is the most simple and easy way
of managing memory, which is.
Smaller can free.
Let think now in terms of the programmer,
who's responsible for allocating the
memory? You say, oh, programmer,
that's it, yes.
But if you are a function,
imagine you're a function and and you
need some dynamic memory because it's not
a local variable,
neither a static variable,
so you need to write in a.
Yeah,
memory that will be allocated dynamically.
Would you allocate or would you ask for
an allocated block where to run?
Which is the fabric.
So who prefers to allocate memory inside
the function? Hands up.
OK,
who prepares to receive our preallocated
memory? Heads up.
OK,
so some that was they were for allocating
inside the function one.
I have to create a responsible to bake.
So I will try it because I really as
clearly I need to be sharing that but to
me I mean if I'm wrong.
The intuition is if I insert the model
inside the function caller,
I will reduce the number of model calls
all around the code.
This will typically help maintenance of
the code because everything is localized
in that.
Function and you declare that that
function requires some memory allocated,
which is totally acceptable as a
management,
someone of the those that say that to
receive allocated memory.
I remember I was just thinking. Yeah,
that's fine. No, it's OK. I mean,
I don't think you ever thought about this
thing.
The argument may be in this way I can
control.
How I allocate the memory in the program?
I don't trust the function.
I wanna be a master of my life and
especially master of my memory.
So I prefer to malloc my memory and then
pass the function the point and the point
the function is a function and.
In a function that is not designed to
have side effects such as modify the
release on my behalf,
which is an acceptable argument too.
And both arguments are so acceptable that
programmers use it both and that is.
One of the main reasons for memory images
in C programs,
because those are human conventions and
humans tend to be to be perfect,
but they're not as perfect as machines,
and so at some point someone will forget
to read.
You get garbage in your memory,
or even worse,
you did something that is still needed.
And this is not because programmers are
stupid,
it's because the end of life of a
dynamically allocated area of your memory.
It may be very,
very far from where the memory has been
originated to the point that you may have
even forget why you allocated that.
You reserving the pointer and you decide
that I did.
I get rid of it without thinking that
that pointer is still valid for someone
else.
OK,
so there is no nothing that there are
conventions and debates,
but basically nothing more than that.
Of course,
if you do the right thing in malloc and
free, the program will be perfect.
But we had an issue.
You had a lot of crashes in your life
that only issue that programs are not
perfect.
OK and and so someone started thinking,
how can I?
Manage automatically the heap.
Are there algorithms that I can invoke?
That may be costly,
but we just learned that even the
simplest form of allocation has some
complexity.
The good thing about the complexity of
the malloc free pair is that is you pay a
single link at least the visit only at.
Small look and free time.
OK,
the rest of all the access to the memory
cost you just the cost of accepting the
memory, nothing.
Of course, if we want to move,
someone may come up with a simple idea.
So if it's true that every.
Piece of the memory can be still useful.
Why don't we declare it?
So every client of the block of a memory
say OK, I'm a client,
I will use it and when the client is not
needing that block anymore, say OK,
I release it.
But this release is not like the three
that goes in three.
But basically says OK one less.
So if I I'm interested in a block of
memory, say one more and if I release it,
I say one less.
Of course if everybody follows.
This convention you will get a counter
that's that tells you how many clients
declare that that block of memory is
still useful and can be deallocated of
course.
If someone forget about trees,
I will end up with some garbage into the
memory.
Garbage is better than than link
references in general because then in
references.
So you the allocate the memory ahead of
time will lead to crashes.
Garbage is simply you are only using the
memory, so in case you forget to.
Taking breeze,
you may end up having a process that
keeps growing in memory until it exhausts
the memory, but it will not be a crash.
So this technique, very very simple,
is called reference counting, right?
So the reference.
Now show me a diagram that.
Uh uh.
Shows uh reference counting so.
Cost.
Now we need a reference counter for every
block.
So one of the nice thing of the.
Uh.
Hmm.
OK.
It already generated the the the main
problem situation for reference counting.
So in this example you have to have
variables A&
B and the object created at one of
reference.
Right.
Uh.
As soon as you introduce another
reference, the counter gets incremented.
This means that every time you add a
reference, you pay an addition,
you have to increment the counter and for
every object you pay 4 bytes.
Which is the reference counter because
that is attached to the object. OK,
so this is costing much more than the
free list because the free list overhead
in terms of space was 0 because we use
the free memory.
To to allocate the structure.
In this case, no.
In this case we allocate a little bit of
family with every allocated blocker to
keep track of the numbers. OK.
20 years ago that would have been a
problem.
Now today we are wasting so much memory
that this is not anymore a problem.
So I'm not going to pretend that this is
terrible. OK,
we will see when we will study runtimes
that the typical object has 12 bytes
occupied.
OK,
so every single thing you you make an
empty object for once. OK,
every single object you allocate a lot of
strings, 12 bytes for each string.
That's it. OK.
Problem.
The first problem is you have to follow
the convention.
So every time you assign the reference to
an object into the memory to a variable,
you have to say plus one.
Right. Uh, every time.
A variable change value and so stops
referencing the object.
You have to issue a decrease.
So this may be explicit.
You will find reference counting
libraries that allows you.
To keep track of the object,
but basically it's you,
the programmer that you're supposed to do
under that and when you release,
you say release. OK,
so basically the department of.
Increasing and decreasing the counter is
is is up on you.
The good thing is that when you free you
may you may make damage.
When you release it you simply say I
already called the address.
Now I'm releasing so it's a safer
operation unless you forgot.
To call Andrea and in fact all the 90s
were dominated by reference counting
because the two main component models at
the level of the operating system POM and
Corpa.
We're using reference counting to decide
when a component was ready to be
allocated and and and at some point
programmer say I am smart,
I'm about to use this object.
But for very small time, so to save time,
I don't call the so that I don't have to
pay in between someone best and dangling
reference and dash. OK, so.
The protocol is easy,
but if you stop using the protocol by
calling at ref before using and releasing
the reference when you're not using it,
it's risky because you may end up with
inconsistent memory.
Now the assignment is an operation that
the compiler understands in general the
runtime of the programming language
understands.
So as remember when yesterday we were
talking about this, we said OK,
whenever there is this statement in
JavaScript.
The Java Vito machine first assigned to
this and then invokes the function.
Similar things.
I mean you see an assignment reference
the compiler in general who can inject
increase the number of the reference and
when you lose that you issue the.
The reference to that object.
This is for instance something that
Python does.
The CPython implementation managed most
of the memory.
Is managed through reference counting.
Motivation is faster than alternatives
problems.
Because Java is using garbage collection,
JavaScript is using garbage collection.
net is using garbage collection.
Go is using garbage collection.
So why all these are not using reference
counting but only garbage collection?
Answer is there is a situation that is
fairly easy to create in which you get.
Loops.
In the references.
So basically if I have object A which
depends.
From object B and vice versa.
So inside the object you've got the
reference one to the other.
These two objects are not referenced by
anyone else.
So they are not reachable,
they are useless,
but they will stay alive because they
have the target to one.
And because we as programmers we tend to
create graphs rather than trees,
we graph the loop.
East.
To the state-of-the-art.
OK and so the risk is we are now
generating garbage because of this
pathologic situation.
In Viton for instance,
whenever there is a loop,
then that part of the memory gets
allocated in a heap which is garbage
collected and it's not reference garbage.
I.
OK.
By now,
I hope to have convinced you that most of
the programming languages are not using
the memory as a single heap.
So the runtime,
the libraries that come with your program,
as we said at some point.
Come with functions that that manage the
the the the which means that you can
malloc live blocks because we said that
the the drawback of the malloc.
The drawback of the model is when you
keep allocating and allocation and this
will fragment and freeze.
OK and also you will pay because you find
the holes that are larger than you need,
so you fragment the least.
Those are the two.
Uh,
problems that you have with the Uh model
operations, but if I manage.
A heap with malloc of large blocks,
same size.
Those are not problems because when you
will browse the prelist,
you will find exactly the same plot
because all the slots are created equal.
OK,
so the typical runtime of a programming
language takes a multi heap approach in
which there is basically the memory of
the processor used as a collection of
heaps and then.
Every heap is managed with different
policies,
so you may perfectly live with explicit
allocation,
reference counting and garbage collection
in the very same program.
Don't think that those are alternatives.
Typically they are combined every heap
count.
With its own memory manager that can be
manually allocated,
explicitly reference counted or garbage
collected, right?
This now lives for the remaining time
with.
The garbage collection so.
I'm not pretending to be exhaustive in
garbage collection.
I'm going to give you enough information
to understand the major garbage
collection strategies adopted by main run
times, java.net, JavaScript, and so on.
OK, uh.
Now can you generate the diagram that
shows a situation to illustrate the mark
and sweep garbage collection mark and
sweep?
So what we learn?
With the.
Uh.
What we learn?
From the reference nothing is that that
basically it would be nice.
That we are able to detect in the heap
the objects that may be referred by the
program in the future. OK,
those that we are sure will not be
referred anymore.
In the rest of the execution of the
program can be free.
Are you convinced by that?
Now let's go back to names.
Yesterday I made I made a statement.
I said in programming.
Names are everything.
It goes through names, you access objects.
OK,
so if you don't have a name that refers
that object, that object is unreachable.
That is, for instance,
very important in security.
Was one of the main technique of security
is hiding,
removing a name so that no way the
program can access that particular name.
OK,
that is one of the itself of security is
exactly play with the names.
It has not great contain this were made
this way.
OK, uh.
Now.
We said in the examples I I made U here.
I said OK, uh.
Oh,
let me let me go very back to the
beginning. There we are. Oh,
the first was Mallo 10. What I did forget.
The variable name. OK,
so basically this value would have been
temporary stored and then discarded.
Can anyone refer to malloc 10? No,
because you've lost the name.
Hmm.
So in the other cases, I said OK.
Void star before equal allocate O what is
before?
A pointer and where it where it is stored.
The way in the stack. OK,
I I I I wrote it in a in a declaration in
a function which is basically a local
variable of a function and so it's in
either in the stack or in the static
memory.
OK,
of course I may also have inside an
object a reference to another object,
as we just commented here in the objects
in the reference counting because objects
may refer.
To other objects. OK,
but eventually when you start following
the chain,
you will end up either in a static memory
or in a local memory,
because everything in dynamic memory.
Ends up in my variable a equal new
something.
OK.
And so and we know as we just commented
if we we we just write new something
without assigning that is lost.
OK, so I don't think.
That uh.
You will be surprised.
Then in garbage collection we start
talking about roots.
Roots are a crucial concept of garbage
collection,
and if you want to really understand the
runtime of a programming language,
you must understand roots.
Roots are key acts.
So here the roots are two local variables,
X&YX refer to object one,
which in turn refers to object 2.
So we know that object 2 is reachable.
Potentially through X passing through
object YY is not referring to anything.
Let's say that indeed we also have object
3 which is not referenced by the rules.
So beware,
because this is a very important element
that will be.
One of the main consideration that made
interest in the rust memory management.
That Monday I'm there will present.
The garage collection say if through the
root an object is reachable,
then I found it.
This will not mean that that object will
be accessed.
It's a conservative approach.
If it's reachable, then don't touch it.
And so if you don't free delete in C++
the object,
if you don't set to null fields or
variable,
you may end up to have a lot of garbage
because the assumption of the.
Uh,
the relation is if it's reachable from
the root, then don't touch it.
And so if you don't bring the point the
reference to other object,
basically you are locking those objects.
So the Martin's weeper is a fairly
intuitive algorithm. So you take an heap,
you use an allocation of the heaper like
the model of three.
Typically garbage collection,
especially garbage collectors,
especially the origin on garbage
collectors.
When implemented in C and they were using
map and free.
So don't think that this thing is
completely separated.
It basically tries to build some
automation on top of the explicit
management. OK,
so it's not a different story.
OK, so basically you say.
How can I tell that object one and object
two are still prepared and object three
is not?
The only thing that I can do is I find
all the rules.
Uh.
I start browsing all the references.
Uh.
Starting from the roots and I mark all
the objects that are still reachable as.
I reach you.
So you're basically making the visit of a
graph.
That is.
And you're marking every node of the
graph where every node is an object.
So the mark phase simply says OK,
object one and object two will be
marketed. Object three,
not because it's in the deeper,
but it will make it accessible anymore.
Sorry, so object three is unmarked.
Therefore,
second phase of the algorithm with.
OK,
so object 3 will be the allocated object
one and object 2 will stay alive.
So Martin's whip is very intuitive.
And it's been used for a very long time
and it's been used with different
approaches.
There is the precise garbage collection,
which means the runtime because you
understand that.
I tricked you in thinking that this thing
is completely easy.
So now suppose that you are a compiler.
You have to lay out data structures so
that the garbage collector software has
complete information about where all the
pointers are.
Because if I have an object which is an
interest distance of of a class with 20
fields,
which of those fields are references?
Which of those are just integers or
clause?
That is relevant.
So the precise garbage collection assumes
that at runtime you know the full layout
of the map.
So basically you can reconstruct fully.
All the pointers and and every part of
the memory you know if it's a value or a
pointer and so you can implement the
bundle script. OK,
there is an alternative approach which
has been popular in during the 90s.
Uh.
And and is that it's not precise.
So basically we release the assumption
that you know the full layout of the
memory. It was popular in C++.
And you say OK if I browse the memory.
And I see something which is an address
that looks like an address to the heap.
I assume it is an address of the heap and
I couldn't see the heap reachable.
So basically you go through the map.
Every four or eight bytes,
depending on the architecture,
you look at the memory,
not knowing whether that is a string,
is an object, is whatever it is, and say,
oh,
this looks like a pointer and this
pointer is a valid would be a valid
pointer in the heap. Let's mark.
So this approach is clearly less precise
because you may be unlucky and you will
find some bytes that look like pointer,
but it's not a pointer.
So you may lock an object that would have
been freed,
but overall was effective and it's been
used in languages that don't have.
Too much documentation at runtime about
the layout of the memory,
and C was exactly one of these languages.
So C is the language that during the
computation throw away a lot of
information.
So the resulting program is semantically
equivalent to the source program,
but all your.
Beautiful class object inheritance will
be thrown away by the compiler and self
by memory.
So in that case precise collection is
impossible because you don't have enough
information at runtime to reconstruct the
full state of the memory.
And so the rules.
OK.
Things that roots are so important that
there are.
Hidden places in the implementation of
the runtime to create fake roots.
Example,
have you ever heard about remoting?
Remoting is the technique in which you
create a remote object.
And then through the network you involve
these methods. OK, so there are protocols,
servers and all these things.
So the server that has the remote object
creates the object,
but that object is not referenced by
anyone.
In that process because the user is on
the other side of the network and so for
instance runtimes have a special place
where these objects are tracked and they
are considered routes as well as the
stack.
And the static memory. OK,
so roots may be complicated because I
give you.
This year I'm not doing it.
20 years ago I was given a class of two
hours in which I extended this.
net runtime during the class by adding a
new instruction to the little machine
called the Load Hello World.
To support the most compiled version
program of the history,
which basically was loading at the Hello
World string on the stack for compiling
and adding the instruction was super easy.
Because clearly the full virtual machine
was designed to be extensible.
So with very few actions I was able to
add the the new instruction, the compiler,
the disassembler,
all the thing were updated automatically.
And then the most difficult thing was to
find a place where to store the Hello
Worlds thing,
because the Hello Worlds thing is an
object and if you create the object
without a root and the first gather
collection, you go with the object.
OK,
so even those who implement the
programming language,
the runtime sometimes need rules to lock
object into the memory because the
garbage collector is pitiless.
When the garbage collector passes,
it turns away everything.
OK, so this is the marking sweep.
We just commented that this,
I mean we said that this can be
implemented in terms of malloc and free.
OK.
But we also commented that if we keep
malloc and free, malloc and free,
small object, large object.
That is a bad thing because we fragment
our and the cost will grow over time.
So the mark and sweep is with JavaStreams
because JavaStreams is just OK streams
are a very good dimension,
so they are the worst.
The enemy of the markets we collect. OK,
do we have alternatives?
Let's invent another algorithm.
The copy collector.
The copy collector, basically.
The heap.
Is divided into semi spaces or I have two
heaps, same thing. OK, so.
When I allocate,
I allocate in the let's say in the front
space allocation.
Now it's easy because I'm just tapping
thing in a time. OK, so first allocation,
first object, second location.
Push their allocation, push and that's it.
I don't care.
When do you trigger the garbage
collection when you fill up?
The available space then I need the
collection now to keep low the cost of
allocation, which is simply an addition.
So you know how much I did allocate of
this.
And I say plus something. So it's very,
very cheap.
I only to remember how much of this has
been already allocated.
It's just a number.
But when I filled up the full space,
then things get, uh, complicated.
So the copy collector basically says.
Um.
I copy all the line objects.
So the mark phase is basically it's the
sweep phase which is different.
The the we we know that it's still
reachable through the rules.
Object one and then object 2 is reachable
through the next field of object one and
so object 2 is still reachable and object
three garbage collectable because it's
energy full. So basically.
You start copying the objects. OK,
so you go through the front space,
you find all the LI objects and you copy
the bytes of those objects in the two
space iterate copying.
OK.
Uh.
And so in the two space I will end U
having the two.
A live object, Sir.
OK.
Now.
I preserved all the objects in the to
space.
The front space contains only useless
memory, the object that have been copied,
so.
I can empty the fool from space, OK,
which is one of you comment is a form of
data fragmentation.
And what do we what did we say?
About the frag,
we have to change the memory of the roots.
We have to go back,
find all the roots that refer to.
Objects that we just copied and we need
to update the pointers so that everything
will stay the same,
otherwise it will be broken.
OK and typically that phase is.
Uh, naming. Um, backpatching.
OK, you go back and batch.
Hopping the the second slide of being
like moving that dust in the other side
and not really really developing mainly.
That's basically the brief spaces.
I didn't comment,
it was implicit is as soon as I finished
to copy what was the two space will
become the front space,
so the current heap and the two space is
considered empty.
You don't even clean it.
You you will continue in the front space
because you copy the in the front space
the the of the line by accumulating so
you can go on and keep some locating
using the front space.
OK,
so basically you start again in the
previous situation and you go in cycles.
In this way you're able to copy for that.
Now it is expensive.
Because we have to browse.
So first of all,
it works only if you're a precise method.
Imprecise collection is not the best type
of collection.
It's not possible with the copy collector
because you can't go and like this. OK,
so first of all, this is applicable only.
Precise memory collection.
So at runtime you know every byte to
which variable belongs.
Second thing,
this is clearly convenient only if at the
at each collection the object that
survives are few.
OK, if I have to copy 70% of the heap,
that will be terrible.
You have to copy a lot of memory to save
only 30%, that would be acceptable.
In terms of efficiency,
also because you will have to backpatch
more and more pointers,
so all the costs will go up and that
would be convenient. OK,
so copy collection is very, very nice.
When you allocate,
you allocate lots of objects that are
shortly needed,
so between a cycle and the next
collection cycle.
Most of the objects are dead.
Because it seems that they just you're
right, technically,
I mean for the sake of explanation,
the helpful AI introduced the.
The front space and to space.
Typically you have the heap that you
allocate of some size where you do the
copy collection as soon as you're ready.
To do the collection itself,
you allocate the new space,
you do the copy collection,
you free the original. OK,
so technically you're not allocating
twice the memory. But yes,
to do the copy collection you need to be
able to allocate.
Another leaf of the same size,
or even smaller,
but in general it's the same size. OK,
so the copy collection works only being
under the assumption that we're not doing
it with the full memory of the process,
but we basically go to the heap pool.
Of the process we take,
let's say one MB and then I need another
MB to do the collection.
I free the MB and then that's acceptable.
OK, that's been very long.
If you try to apply this algorithm to the
full memory process,
that would be impractical in impractical.
So it requires A sophisticated
hierarchical way of managing heaps.
So basically you create heaps from the
process memory and then every heap is
managed internally with a different
policy.
That we're about to see that is where the
copy collection is used.
So the copy collection basically works
well under the assumption that most of
the object that they are located in the
front space.
When I trigger the garbage collection
because I exhausted the the space,
those objects, most of them are dead.
So the number of objects that I will copy,
the number of pointers that I have to
backpack is limited.
Sounds a lot like the streams of Java.
OK, so the copy collection,
if you want to think one main big example
of copy collection are immutable things
because you need to compose them.
You keep generating new objects and
deleting old one every time in your
programming.
Title string plus the value plus on this
tree which is every day.
Thank your copy collection for its
efficiency. OK,
because you are generating 3 strings,
generate the 4th by combining the three
and then throw away the.
The the first three things.
So that's typical of screen manipulation,
which is big, so it's OK.
But if we if our objects in our program,
I don't know a computer game are not
strings.
And they are not so shortly because in a
computer, in a computer game, the scenery,
so all the the the the free rent in here
is for very long.
Time the same.
I'll be a very good player and keep
changing scenes.
The reality is that the copy collection
is not such a good option because most of
the objects allocated are alive.
So all the operation will cost because
you have to move a lot of memory and
clearly that is linear in the number of
bytes you're moving and you will
backpatch a a large number of elements.
So in that case it's not convenient.
Mark and sweep, on the other hand,
suffer a lot if you allocate, allocate,
allocate, allocate,
OK and so fragments when you do the
JavaScript.
So thank you.
The olicy is bound to the lifespan of an
object.
Which is clearly empirical because it
depends by the particular program.
I just outlined.
So if we're doing web application,
lots of strings because we keep
generating HTML computer games,
long-lived objects.
Those are main classes,
but you can make a runtime for every
application so you can say OK.
Let's try to combine uh.
Uh.
Uh hierarchical uh garbage collector with
the copy in Gen. 0 and mark and.
In Gen. 1.
Uh.
So you have once you get used to the idea
that there is no.
Once you get used to the idea that there
is no single leap in your memory process,
but also you can have multiple leaps and
every.
And heap is basically an array of bytes
and every heap can be managed with
different policies then.
OK. Oh.
Yeah.
For decal.
GC with the Gen. 0 copy collector and Gen.
1 mark and sweet.
So the idea is if we allocate dynamically
heaps and manage heaps in with these
policies, we can combine different.
Policies and empirically.
Most of the objects allocated by a
program either are very short-lived,
looks a string,
or they tend to be long-lived. Of course,
there are magic numbers when we will
browse.net.
One time we we will find magic numbers
with comments that says empirically we
did the test and this is the best number
we can for all the tests we run. OK,
so there's no better way.
It's empirical evidence. It's not theory.
OK, but nevertheless works.
The work works thanks to this,
so it's OK and and basically what you do,
you say OK.
I allocate generate heaps in generation,
so we call generation 0 where the new
operation will take place.
That is generation 0. OK,
so the allocation is always super fast.
We said it's just plus something.
Uh.
Then as soon as we finish Gen. 0 heap,
we fill it up. We do the mark and sweep,
sorry, the copy collection,
but we copy the objects in another heap
that is called generation one.
Which is managed using the mark and sweep
and eventually the free list. OK,
because we know that if that object
survived so long,
it's likely to live and so this long live
will reduce the fragmentation.
Of the market sweep managed the heap,
which was basically the major back back
back back back drop.
OK, so basically the idea is you in Gen.
0 you allocate objects, you collect,
you are, you move objects to Gen. one,
those Boolean lead.
You backpatch,
so you pay your backpatching and then you
go and ideally you can iterate this
process and you can introduce generation
2, generation 3 and so on.
So I mean you can complicate things as
much as you want.
But basically, uh, the uh.
Most of the time,
generational garbage collection includes
a couple of generations, zero and one,
plus a large object heap,
because large objects, when are allocated,
typically are long-lived.
Uh, I don't remember exactly the number,
but it's something around 1.
5 kilobyte in the run.
net runtime is the minimum size of a
large collected object.
So in case you're making in your program
new.
An object which is 2 kilobytes,
then automatically the runtime will use
the large object heap,
which is not a copy collector.
It's just a Martin sweep because copying
1.
5 kilobytes is expensive and it's
pointless to do the copy OK.
Remember when I said about the Xbox,
the two version of the CLR, etc.
Now I can tell the full story, the.
net implementation for it was 2005.
net implementation for Xbox.
Was removing the generational garbage
collection and replacing it by a mark and
sweep collector.
Reason because you're not allocating so
many strings.
Which are the main customers of the copy
collector and basically the copy
collector were was slowing down all the
games.
OK.
To witness how empiric evaluation is
dominant in this automatic memory
management.
Don't think that there is something much
better than this.
I mean these are strategies we said that.
Imperfect,
because if the programmer does not
cooperate and do not release reference,
you keep alive object that should be
reclaimed and so it's not even a
guarantee that you're not generating
garbage.
The only thing that a precise garbage
collector, or even an unprecise, ensures.
Is that you have no dangling references.
Dangling references are pointers that
refers to memory areas that are not valid
anymore,
which is the worst situation for a
program because typically we'll end up in
a crash because the program will.
Interpret that pointer and the memory in
the wrong way. We write the memory,
corrupt the memory and eventually the
system will crash. For instance,
the Ariane 5 rocket that I mentioned at
the very first class.
OK, so.
I think it was a long journey.
Now I hope you know a little bit more
about memory management.
Memory management is something that you
have to consider every time you write a
single line of your program.
Because memory management is 50% to 80%
of the time of your program was better
because it's a take from the memory,
copy in the register, add,
subtract or whatever put back in the
memory.
Starts again.
So that is the most intensive,
one of the most intensive operations.
You know what are exception to that? CERN.
At CERN they use a lot of Monte Carlo.
You know, Monte Carlo, Monte Carlo, you.
You generate random numbers and do things.
That is something that stays mostly in
the CPU and so it's not memory intensive,
but any other program I know of and in
fact you know that.
There is this physical law by which if
you want a high clock in your CPU,
you have to reduce the the core count. OK,
CERN is buying a lot of CPU with super
high clock,
fewer clock count because they need just
to go fast in Monte Carlo, but.
That is so exceptional that they even
order CPUs different from the rest of the
world for that. OK,
but the rest of the world requires memory.
And just to give you a real world example,
you know what is the bandwidth of the
memory today?
Depending how much memory you can
transmit per second.
You have to.
If you want to become an advanced
programmer,
you have to understand that because you
have to dimension your program under that
assumption.
So the high bandwidth memory for Intel
today is one terabyte per second.
The high bandwidth memory for NVIDIA is
one terabyte per second.
OK,
that is the HPM and it gives you the idea
who how much is important memory to CPU
transfer, right?
See you.
Unfortunately I will not be there,
but I mean I will try to attend remotely.
I will be traveling Monday.
There will be Andrea that will introduce
you to Rust.
Thank you.